<post>
  <title>Checking MIME type for cross domain Silverlight hosting</title>
  <slug>checking-mime-type-for-cross-domain</slug>
  <author>Mark Heath</author>
  <pubDate>2009-09-15 13:39:00</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2010-09-23 15:20:22</lastModified>
  <content>&lt;p&gt;I recently ran into some problems trying to embed a Silverlight application in a web page hosted on another server. It seems that to do so, you must have your MIME type for .xap files correctly configured (should be &lt;strong&gt;application/x-silverlight-app&lt;/strong&gt;). Interestingly, this is not required if you are hosting the .xap file in a web page on the same domain.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for me, my shared Linux hosting provider allows no way of configuring or even viewing the MIME types. After searching in vain for a utility that would let me have a look and see what MIME type a given URL was returning, I wrote my own test function. It turns out to be possible in just two lines of code – create a WebRequest, and examine the ContentType of the WebResponse.&lt;/p&gt;  
&lt;pre class="brush: csharp;"&gt;[TestFixture]
public class MimeTypeChecker
{
    [Test]
    public void CheckSilverlightMimeTypeIsCorrect()
    {
        string mimeType = GetMimeType(&amp;quot;http://www.mydomain.com/mysilverlightapp.xap&amp;quot;);
        Assert.AreEqual(&amp;quot;application/x-silverlight-app&amp;quot;, mimeType);
    }

    public string GetMimeType(string url)
    {
        WebRequest request = WebRequest.Create(url);
        WebResponse response = request.GetResponse();
        return response.ContentType;
    }
}&lt;/pre&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Update:&lt;/b&gt; If your .xap file is hosted on an Apache server on Linux, you can set up the MIME types correctly by creating a &lt;b&gt;.htaccess&lt;/b&gt; file. This can be put in the root of your hosting space, or just in the folder containing the .xap file. It only needs the .xap registration, but the example I show below configures xaml and xbap as well:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class="brush: plain;"&gt;AddType application/x-silverlight-app .xap
AddType application/xaml+xml .xaml
AddType application/x-ms-xbap .xbap&lt;/pre&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>true</ispublished>
  <categories>
    <category>Silverlight</category>
  </categories>
  <comments />
</post>